<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The copie of a letter sent by a learned physician to his friend wherein are detected the manifold errors vsed hitherto of the apothecaries, in preparing their compositions, as sirropes, condites, conserues, pilles, potions, electuaries, losinges, &amp;c: wherein also the reader shall finde a farre better manner how to preserue and correct the same ...</title>
            <author>I. W., fl. 1586.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1586</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14595</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24906</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104450</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840188</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840188</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4664</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14595)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4664)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 400:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The copie of a letter sent by a learned physician to his friend wherein are detected the manifold errors vsed hitherto of the apothecaries, in preparing their compositions, as sirropes, condites, conserues, pilles, potions, electuaries, losinges, &amp;c: wherein also the reader shall finde a farre better manner how to preserue and correct the same ...</title>
                  <author>I. W., fl. 1586.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Wolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1586?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated and signed at end: S. the 21. of this present March. 1586. .. I.W.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Materia medica --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:4664:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4664:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The copie of a letter ſent by a learned</hi> Phyſician to his friend, wherein are detected the manifold errors vſed hitherto of the Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, in preparing their compoſitions, as Sirropes, Condites, Conſerues, Pilles, Potions, Electuaries, Loſinges, &amp;c: Wherein alſo the reader ſhall finde a farre better manner how to preſerue and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the ſame, to the great honor and credite of the Phyſician, and comfort of the ſicke: but chieflie and eſpeciallie to the great prayſe and glorie of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight welbeloued Cooſin &amp; deere friend, theſe are to certifie you, that I haue receiued your letters da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the third of Marche, wherein I perceyue you ſeeme to be ſorowful, for that I am ſo much addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to this new ſect of <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> called by the name and title of <hi>Paracelſians:</hi> a more odious and contemptible name (I perſwade my ſelfe) you could not haue beſtowed vpon it, then to intitle it <hi>A new ſect.</hi> But ſith you cannot iuſtlie prooue it, I can the better brooke the accuſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; it ſeemeth that you neuer read many of <hi>Paracel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> his workes, nor yet that booke lately ſet forth
<pb facs="tcp:4664:2"/>
by Maſter B. in our mother tounge: which if you had done, I hope you would not haue cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it the <hi>New Phiſicke.</hi> For in thoſe authors you ſhall find this propoſition truely and manifeſtly confirmed, <hi>that it had his beginning with our firſt father Adam,</hi> and ſo from time to time hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued vntill this day: but indeed ſo amplified and enlarged of late, and brought vnto euery mans ſight (that hath both his eies) by the long labour and infinite paines of <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> that it ſeemeth to be borne a new with him. I cannot therefore be a little grieued at you, nor take ſmall offence at your ſcandalous and ſlanderous termes, which from the corrupt coller of your angrie mind you haue giuen forth againſt him. For haue you not called him Heretike, Coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, Dronkard, Iugler, Toſpot, Aleknight, &amp;c? Ah deere Cooſin, did you euer read any hereſie in his bookes? if you had, then were it your du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to haue named where; but if you ſpeake it onely vpon heareſay (as many of your coate do commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly) then are you greatly to be reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. I aſſure you, I haue read ſo many bookes of his as are extant and find not any ſpot of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie in him, but contrariwiſe a pure and true Chriſtian, a friend and fauourer of the flocke of Chriſt, &amp; a great enemie to the enemies of Ieſu, as the deuil, pope, &amp; turke. And who euer wrote more againſt coniuring then he did, againſt Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gromancie, ſorcerie, witchcraft, gluttony, and
<pb facs="tcp:4664:2"/>
ſuche like abhominations: repayre to his bookes <hi>De occulta Philoſophia,</hi> and <hi>De Magia,</hi> there ſhall you finde it. Iudge him not then good Cooſin by the mouth of his enemies (who ſpeake of enuie) no more then you would by the verdict of his friendes, but trie him by his owne wordes.</p>
            <p>Me thinkes you goe very neere him to find fault with his drinking, I think you haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten what Countryman hee was. Can you giue the Dier leaue to quaffe, &amp; the Smith to carrowſe, and will you grudge <hi>Paracelſus</hi> to drinke meaſurably and with reaſon? remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber with your ſelues (for I ſpeake to you and all your companie and fauorites) that <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celſus</hi> ſate not all day on a cuſhion with a pen in his hand, but was occupied both night and day in diſtilling, ſubliming, calcining, mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, fixing, reſoluing, coagulating, reuerbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating, digeſting, &amp; cementing, which things could not be performed without great horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſtrong fires, which muſt needes cauſe a man to haue a iuſt quarrell to the cuppe. But that hee was a drunkard, or tooke more then he could beare away, you cannot prooue, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doo his workes declare. As for his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, you ſay he had none, if you cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of diuers tounges, learning, as I thinke you doo, he had the knowledge and vſe of as many as any author you haue, and wrote in
<pb facs="tcp:4664:3"/>
more. <hi>Galene</hi> wrote but in one tongue, &amp; that his mother tongue, no more did <hi>Hippocrates</hi> or <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> neither can you certainely ſay that they had any more: but hee wrote as well in the Latine tongue, as in the Germane tongue, which you may perceiue if you pleaſe to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe his booke <hi>De Tartaro.</hi> Hee was alſo a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in <hi>Baſilia,</hi> which hee could not performe without great learning, aske <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> he will ſay the ſame.</p>
            <p>Moreouer you lay to his charge that his medecines were nothing but poiſon, wherof you nominate ſome particulars, <hi>viZ. Oile of Vitriole, the glaſſe of Antimonie, the precipitate of Quickeſiluer,</hi> and the <hi>rust of Iron</hi> (as you terme it). As for the glaſſe of <hi>Antimonie,</hi> if it doth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then well you doo him great wrong to burthen him with it, for you ſhal not finde in all his works that he did once name it. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie not but you may find in diuerſe places of his workes where he maketh mention of <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared Antimonie,</hi> and what great vertue it hath in curing many diſeaſes, if you ſuppoſe that he meant the glaſſe thereof, you are farre de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued, there is great oddes betweene that &amp; the <hi>Magiſterie eſſence,</hi> or <hi>tincture</hi> thereof. If you account and eſteeme <hi>Mathi: Geſnerus, Ander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacus</hi> and ſuch like for <hi>Paracelſians,</hi> as I thinke they would haue prooued if they had liued a litle longer: I confeſſe that at that time the
<pb facs="tcp:4664:3"/>
glaſſe of <hi>Antimonie</hi> was had in great eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: ſo that ſome of them ſo oft as they named it, would terme it <hi>Stibium nostru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> others would not ſticke to call it the Philoſophers ſtone: yea they auouched that they would do more good with it (in three dayes) in any deſperate diſeaſe, then they could with their Methodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call medicines in a whole moneth. And ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as any great griefe came to their handes, whether would they runne for ſuccour but to the ſame glaſſe? What would they haue done thinke you if they could haue obtained the perfect preparation therof, that is to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate him quite from his impurities, which is nothing performed in vitrifiyng him? For in this glaſſe, the earthly ſulphur is ſo mingled with his <hi>Mercurie,</hi> that he is made rather worſe then better, and ſo of force he muſt do more harme then good. And you <hi>Galeniſts</hi> cannot ſo much diſprayſe it, but we doo as much &amp; euer did abhor it, for our Maſter hath taught vs a farre better order how to vſe it.</p>
            <p>The oile of <hi>Vitriole,</hi> if ſo be it be wel drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>rectified,</hi> and with the <hi>ſpirite</hi> of wine well <hi>circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated,</hi> vntill it come to a pleaſant tartnes: not onely we haue found great commoditie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as oft as wee had neede to aſſwage thirſt, open obſtructions, or withſtand the maligni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of feuers, but a great many of your opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on haue highly commended the ſame, and
<pb facs="tcp:4664:4"/>
will not giue it a <hi>Paracelſian</hi> name (for they thought it not good enough for ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent extractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) but they haue giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it a new name, and termed it their artificiall <hi>Melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie.</hi> If <hi>Dioſcorides</hi> durſt miniſter a dramme thereof vnprepared, why ſhould wee feare to giue a ſcruple of it, when it is purged from his venome by the fire. As by the contrary effect it doth appeare, for he gaue it to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke vomite, we bring it to ſuch a paſſe, that it becomes a ſingular medecine to ſtay vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite. He ſaith it heateth, and wee make it a great cooler. It appeareth therefore that hee (as he commonly did) reſpected onely the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous qualitie thereof.</p>
            <p>You ſeeme alſo greatly to reprooue vs for the powder of Iron, &amp; terme it the ruſt. What ayle you? what doo you? what meane you to be ſo partial in diſpraiſing of that in vs, which you allow in your owne authors? you can not inuey againſt vs therein, but you muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude them alſo. And is there no difference betweene <hi>Crocus Martis</hi> reuerberated into an inpalbable powder and the droſſe of Iron. If you had euer ſeene them together, you would ſay there is not ſo much difference betweene fine flower and courſe branne: and yet <hi>Dioſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corides</hi> may be permitted to vſe the one, and poore <hi>Paracelſus</hi> blamed for occupiyng the other, though he made as ſmall account of it
<pb facs="tcp:4664:4"/>
(as if you read him diligently you ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue) as you haue done or can doo for your liues, becauſe he knew a far better and more perfect preparation of the ſame, <hi>viZ.</hi> firſt to diſſolue it, then to ſeparate his impurities.</p>
            <p>Now you muſt be anſwered concerning <hi>Precipitate,</hi> to ſpeake what I thinke and not to flatter you, I tell you plainly that you are ſo ignorant in theſe medecines, that ſilence were the beſt anſwere I could giue. But were you not my very freend &amp; louing Cooſin, I ſhould ſhape you an anſwere accordingly, for it were too much to prouide you good meate, and to force it vpon you. If you do meane that <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitate</hi> which is commonly vſed and to bee ſold at the Poticaries, fixed wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the ſpirite of Allome Coperoſe, and Salt Peter; you miſtake the matter: for <hi>Paracelſus</hi> neuer durſt mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter it outwardly, albeit <hi>Mathiolus</hi> with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe other haue done it, and that with ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular good ſucceſſe as they affirme. I pray you beſtow a little looking on, and peruſing of <hi>Paracelſus</hi> his bookes, and there ſhall you find <hi>Mercurie</hi> prepared three ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of waies. The firſt is fixed, the ſecond ſeperated from his impurities, the third and chiefeſt brought whole to a perfect ripeneſſe. Concerning the firſt, if it be ſo fixed that it will abide the fire, which your common Precipitate will not doo, then ſhall you finde him a ſingular good
<pb facs="tcp:4664:5"/>
medecine in ſundry grieuous diſeaſes, but there are diuerſe wayes to doo it, and after it be done it requireth to bee dulcerated and waſhed from his <hi>Aqua fortis,</hi> I doo not meane your common <hi>Aqua fortis.</hi> Notwithſtanding if it be fixed without any liquor, onely in the ſunne, which hath bin brought to paſſe, then neede he not any dulcerations, but of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is ſo ſweete as hony. In all theſe fixings there is no ſeparation of his poyſon, but it is ſo bound that it cannot worke his will ſo ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as he did before, although ſomewhat hee doth, as by vomiting and ſpitting it doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. Therefore if hee be ſeperated from his venome, as ſeperation may be made, then were he more of value then all the compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and drugges in the Apothecaries ſhops, then ſhould the french diſeaſe be quickly cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red without ſtiffeneſſe of the ioynts, and loſſe of teeth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Then ſhould theſe woodden Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians lacke worke which crie out the diet, the diet, and nothing but the diet, to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, to the diet. The third and laſt way where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>Paracelſus</hi> maketh mention, is performed not onely by ſeparation of his impuritie, but afterward alſo to exalt him, by adding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a fitte Sulphure, and placing him in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable clymate for a certaine ſpace, that hee becomes as an Eagle, that is, expelleth all ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous impurities of mans body, euen as
<pb facs="tcp:4664:5"/>
the Eagle deuoureth the venemous beaſtes: hee becommeth a Lion able to vanquiſh all impurities, whatſoeuer we receaue from the Animals.</p>
            <p>Thus much I haue thought good to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere you, concerning ſuch medecines as you obiected in your letters againſt vs: now (if you will giue me liue a little) I will be ſo bold as to examine your medecines, whereof you make ſuch boaſtes, and what cures you haue done with them. If you did any, I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it was through the Lord his bleſſing of that bad medicine, rather then by certaine ſkilfulneſſe or any cunning, as by that which hereafter followeth (if you will with patience reade it) ſhall plainely appeare vnto you. And firſt to beginne with your <hi>decoctions, conſerues,</hi> and <hi>ſyrrupes,</hi> all which are compounded ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>hearbes, fruites, flowers, rootes,</hi> or <hi>iuyces,</hi> by adding eyther honye or ſugar. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, if a <hi>conſerue</hi> of <hi>flowers</hi> be to bee made, then you preſcribe that vnto each pound of flowers there be added two pound of ſugar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if iuices or decoctions you put equal waight, and ſometimes more or leſſe as you thinke good. Then are they put vp in paynted potts till the ſicke ſende for them, and (ſelie ſoule) many times he giueth a noble for that, which doth him not two pennie woorth of good. No, you will ſay, are not theſe excellent good
<pb facs="tcp:4664:6"/>
ſimples, as roſes, roſemarie flowers, ſteca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos, mints, violets, and ſuch like. Yes, wee confeſſe that the hearbs are good and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, but as they are ordered by you they lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle auayle. Is not wheat, rye, and barlie good and wholeſome too? and yet they being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into the body, nature findeth two ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in them, the one good, but little in qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tity, which ſhe retaineth, the other droſſe and great in quantitie, which ſhee expelleth: part by ſiege, part by vrine, &amp; part by ſweate. If then nature findeth two ſubſtances in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing, the one good the other bad, why ſhould not you doo the like, who ought in all your doings to imitate her? And yet contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to her rules you doo not onely not ſeeke to ſeparate theſe impurities, which euery thing, ſeeme it neuer ſo wholeſome, is ioyned withall, but like vndiſcreete and vnreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you adde more vnto it, for to a pound of flowers, hearbes or rootes, whereof ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times 15. ounces and an halfe, and ſomtimes more is baggage, you adde as much ſugar therevnto to help afterward. But your anſwer is ready, for you will ſay that ſugar and honie are added for to preſerue thoſe and other things from putrifaction. I will aske you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine what that is which putrifieth, &amp; which of the two parts, whether is it that which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture retayneth, or that which ſhee expelleth?
<pb facs="tcp:4664:6"/>
I thinke you will anſwere according to truth and reaſon, that the things which nature dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth out by excrement are eſpecially ſubiect to putrifaction. But it may bee that you will make an other anſwere and more fit for your purpoſe, ſaying that they both do both of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> corrupt and putrifie together. Then would I demaund which of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> putrifieth each other? I know you will be loth to giue iudgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your ſelfe. Well then let ſeparation be made, let arte imitate nature. Let there be an artificiall ſtomacke deuiſed, let 4. buſhels of roſes be put thereinto, and after digeſtion &amp; ſeparation, you ſhall find in one ſide halfe an ounce of pure Sulphur or oile, wherein all the vertue of that great quantitie conſiſteth, and on the other ſide all the reſt droſſie matter &amp; impuritie. Now which of theſe two doo laſt longeſt I think you do not doubt, but wil af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme it to be that which is ſmall in quantity: for that is knowen to laſt many yeares, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not many houres. The like may be ſaid of all the reſt of your ſirrupes whatſoeuer, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be made of hearbes, flowers, rootes, iuices or fruits, in that there is not any of all theſe but they abound with impuritie, which muſt be preſerued, or els they tend not onely to putrifactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but do alſo deſtroy that eſse<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that is ioyned with them. Thus may you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue that your indeuour is and alwaies hath
<pb facs="tcp:4664:7"/>
beene, to preſerue that which nature abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth: to pound or pouder that which ſhe by al meanes expelleth: for you ſee that your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration is cleane co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to her: for ſhe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth by ſubſtraction and diuiſion, but you la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to adde &amp; multiply: you are very expert in addition and multiplication, <hi>Natura paucis contenta,</hi> Nature is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent with a little or a few things, haue you forgotten this rule? doo you deale well with her, in that when ſhe ſendeth to you for ayd, telling you that her ſtomacks are weake and not able to digeſt and ſeparate as they were woont to doo, to ſend her iuices of hearbes or flowers, laden both with their owne impurities, and burdened with the filth of hony or ſugar, make ſeparation of either of them, &amp; you ſhall find ſuch ſtore of filth that you would bee loth to looke vpon it. Oh in what eſtate is nature in now, that when ſhee was well &amp; ſtrong ſhe digeſted but one pound of ſubſtance for an ounce of ſuſtenance. And now ſhe muſt, beyng weake and feeble, digeſt three pound for aſmuch? is this to helpe her or to hinder her? doth ſhee not abhorre your aide euer after? doth ſhee not riſe ſo oft as ſhe ſees it? Let the ſicke be iudge, which once ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing taſted of it, muſt winke when ſhe ſhould receaue it againe. How much then is nature, the ſicke man, and all other diſeaſed perſons bound to prayſe God for <hi>Paracelſus</hi> &amp; all his
<pb facs="tcp:4664:7"/>
diſciples, who haue deuiſed ſtomacks to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare and ſeparate for them as oft as they haue neede of Phiſicke. They haue in ſtore <hi>Salia olea</hi> and <hi>Mercuries,</hi> wherof one ſcruple doth more delight her the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an whole pound either of ſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupes, conſerues or Iuleps. Yea I haue ſeene that 9. graynes of a vegetable ſalt hath more quenched the burning heat of an ague, then 9. drams of the ſirrupe of Violets, Cichorie or Limons could haue done, which thing I know you will ſcarſly beleeue, becauſe your maiſter <hi>Galene</hi> ſaith that euery ſalt is of an heating and drying nature: of which opinion I was once, vntill I came vnto another ſchoole, where be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the Anatomie of ſaltes, I found not only <hi>Salia mundificantia, coagulantia, conſolidan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, diaphoretica, diaretica,</hi> but alſo <hi>Sitim &amp; ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorem reſoluentia.</hi> So likewiſe there are <hi>Mercurij mitigantes, clarificantes, exhilarantes, conſumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, confortantes &amp; regenerantes,</hi> and <hi>Sulphura ſomnifera, narcotica, mitigantia, concoquentia, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyna, attrahentia</hi> and <hi>ſiſtentia,</hi> are in like ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner to be found in hearbes, parts of beaſts mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus deare Coſin, you ſee that I haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſerues, condites &amp; ſirrupes to be of no force, &amp; compounded contrary to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that they are rather ſawces then mede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, and more meete for Cookes then Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, &amp; haue ſhewed you that the ſalts, oiles
<pb facs="tcp:4664:8"/>
and liquors of hearbes, rootes, ſeedes, fruits, &amp; flowers, are far more excellent in ſtrength and operation, but in during alſo and eaſines of miniſtring to the partie, in that they are purged of their impurities, and quite deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from their lothſome ſauour and ill taſtes, which muſt needes be a great comfort to the ſicke and diſeaſed. Make triall and you ſhall find that three drops of the oile of Stecados, or three drops of the oile of Roſes, or three drops of the oile of Nutmegs, will doo more good in ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gthning the braine, then 6. ou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the ſirupes prepared with the ſame ſimples. Likewiſe three drops of the oile of Poppie, or of the oile of Nenuphar, will more auayle in cauſing ſleepe and reſt, then three ounces of their ſirrupes. Moreouer three graines of the ſalt of <hi>Radiſh</hi> rootes, <hi>Eringus</hi> roots, or <hi>Reſthar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> rootes will more profite in diſeaſes of the raines &amp; bladder, then 6. ounces of their ſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupes. Alſo three drops of the oile of mints in ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gthening the ſtomacke, three drops of the Mercurie of Bugloſſe in comforting the heart is of more force then ſix ounces of their ſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupes, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now will I indeuour diligently to take a view and ſuruey of your purgations, to ſee whether you are wiſer in preparing of them, then of your other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fections. I thinke it will fal out according to the Welchma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s prouerb,
<pb facs="tcp:4664:8"/>
Droth in gooth: one bad the other worſe: you perceiued by the euill accidents which did enſue, that there was not almoſt any of them but had an ill qualitie ioined with him, as the Poet ſaith:
<q>Omnis commoditus ſua fert incommoda ſecum.</q>
As for example, <hi>Sena</hi> did breed winde, <hi>Rubarb</hi> did drie the body ouermuch, <hi>Agarick</hi> ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw the ſtomack, <hi>Scammonie</hi> weakened the liuer and intrailes, <hi>Caſsia</hi> feebled the raines, <hi>Colocinthis</hi> bred the bloodie flixe, <hi>Euforbium</hi> inflamed the whole body, &amp;c there is not one of them to be found without fault. What or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der tooke you then, did you purge any of theſe from their euill qualities? not one, but by al meanes went about to hide and beguile nature, as for ilſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, to beguile the noſe (for many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue a very ill ſauour) you went to the perfumers &amp; bought Muske, yee went alſo to the Cookes for hony and ſugar, that you might betray the taſt therof: and leaſt the ſight and ouglines thereof ſhould bewray it, you ran to the goldſmithes to buy gold leaues to couer it.</p>
            <p>Thus were theſe poore watchmen betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed beyng placed as porters of nature to ſee that no enemy come in. After the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner you thought to flatter the ſtomacke, liuer, and hart, with Maſtick, Ginger, oile of ſweete Almonds, quinces, long pepper, gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me <hi>Traga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganth,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4664:9"/>
commin, &amp; ſpike, but in vaine: for they would ſee a litle neerer to it, although their watchmen were beguild, the ſtomacke would by al meanes aſſay to caſt it vp againe, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes doth, and neuer would miſſe, were not theſe varlets <hi>Maſtick Tragaganth</hi> &amp;c. ready to take theſe traytors parts. The heart riſeth, falleth ſendeth forth cold ſweats, wherby you may plainely perceaue that he is not pleaſed with theſe naughty gheſts, albeit they bring in their hands, roſes, cloues, ſpikenard, lignum aloes, cinnamon and ſuch like trifles, hee will not haue his head broke, and his cap put on. And as little account makes the liuer of your three kindes of Saunders. What is the cauſe if you be asked the queſtion, you make a ſleeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe anſwere? But go amongſt the common people where a man may better be inſtructed by Lady experience, then by reading and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoluing your methodicall volumes, the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar ſort I ſay, will tell you that euery purgatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is a poyſon. At which ſaying (when I was in your predicament and opinion) I haue often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times laughed: but ſince the time that I came to the knowledge of the art of ſeparation, I finde it the truth, and no ridiculous matter which they haue ſet downe. For not onely <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locinthis, Eleborus, Turbith, Scammonie, Hermoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctily, Euforbium,</hi> and ſuch like haue their impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, but <hi>Polipodie, Sene, Manna, Tamarinds,
<pb facs="tcp:4664:9"/>
Caſsia, Rubarbe,</hi> haue alſo their filthines, though not in that extremitie. This could the ſimple and vnlearned find out: &amp; yet you great clarkes with al your learning &amp; ſkill could not eſpy the ſame, which tendeth to your great diſcredite, &amp; hath brought you &amp; your art into ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempt, that they had rather ſtand to the mercy of the diſeaſe then to meddle with your ſlubbered &amp; polluted medecines. Yea, the wiſe herby are brought into this opinion and conceyt, that whoſoeuer vſeth much phyſick can not be very healthie euer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And I haue heard diuerſe ſay, that they haue marked, &amp; ſundry times obſerued, that if a man had taken a purgation co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fected after your accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed manner, &amp; the ſame had not wrought &amp; taken effect in his body: if that he did not ſhortly after breake out into itch or ſcabs, he ſhould feel ſuch an inward weakenes, that a long time after he ſhould not be his owne man againe. The cauſe wherof may be gathered by that which we ſpake before, in that theſe your adulterate medecines, are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fected only by addition without ſeparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that which is hurtfull, for then the pure not working, but the vnpure getting the maſtrie hath his effect, and worketh his will, to the great hurt of the patient, &amp; ſlander of our honorable ſcience of phyſicke. But you to ſaue your owne credite wil make a ſluttiſh excuſe, &amp; ſay the party would not be ruled, &amp; hath either taken colde or kept an ill diet, and ſo leaue him oftentimes in
<pb facs="tcp:4664:10"/>
worſe caſe then you found him. Alas good Coſin, why are you then diſpleaſed &amp; out of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie with ſuch perſons as do aduiſe, and of good will exhort you, not to couer the venome of <hi>Sca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie</hi> with Quinces, the windines of <hi>Sene</hi> with ginger, the drineſſe of <hi>Rubarbe</hi> with ſuccorie, the fretting of <hi>Colocinthis</hi> with gum <hi>Tragaganth,</hi> the burning and firie qualities of <hi>Euforbium</hi> with the iuice of lillies, the ſtinking ſauour of <hi>Sagapenum</hi> with muske, the bitternes of <hi>Aloes</hi> with ſugar? but haue brought to light the manner how to take quite away theſe incommodities: that whether they worke or worke not there ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no hurt come to the party. Which that you may bring to paſſe, you ſhall not need to ſend vnto <hi>Atticum</hi> for fine hony, nor into the Eaſt for <hi>Sau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders,</hi> nor into <hi>Spain</hi> for ſugar, nor into <hi>Italy</hi> for Anniſeeds, but only beſtow a litle mony with the poore Collier, &amp; as much at the Glaſhouſe, &amp; with theſe two things of ſmall coſt you may draw the pure ſpirit of wine, which in few daies will ſeperate the good from the bad, the vertue from the venome, the pure from the vnpure, without any hinderance at all to the operation of the good. Neither need you to feare this, that your medecines will take any heat thereby, to cauſe any annoyance to the ſicke, in that the menſtrue being rightly drawne will with euery ſmall heat euaporate quite away. But if there be any heat left it will be nothing ſo much as is in yours, by adding Ginger, Cinna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,
<pb facs="tcp:4664:10"/>
&amp;c: the which notwithſtanding you are woont to giue in hote feuers. Now your ſimples being prepared in manner aforeſaid, you may giue <hi>Colocinthis, Euforbium, Eleborus, Elaterium,</hi> &amp; <hi>Sca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monie</hi> ſo ſafely, as you may miniſter the whole ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce either of <hi>Sene, Manna,</hi> or <hi>Caſsia.</hi> Thus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; extracted the eſſence of each ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple purger, then may you compound if you liſt <hi>Cholagoga, Phlegmagoga, Melanagoga, Hydragoga,</hi> yea &amp; <hi>Panchimagoga,</hi> whereunto if you adde alſo the eſſence either of <hi>Stecados, Mintes, Betonie, Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs, Cloues, Maſtick, Cinnamon. &amp;c:</hi> not that you may correct the medicine, but that thereby you may obtaine a double co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie, for your pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation ſhall both euacuate and ſtrengthen. In triall whereof you ſhall finde halfe a ſcruple of the eſſence either of <hi>Colocinth, Euforb, Hermodact, Turbith, Lapidis, Cyaney, &amp;c.</hi> to be more auailable and effectuall in <hi>Hemicrania, Cephalalgia, Hydrope, Paralyſi, Lepra, Melancholia, Arthritide ophthalmia,</hi> then two drams either of <hi>pillulae aureae, pillulae Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiae, pillulae ſine quibus eſſe noli, pillulae ex Eſula, ex hermodactilis</hi> or <hi>pillulae è lapide Cyaneo &amp; ceteris,</hi> &amp; one ſcruple of the eſſence either of <hi>Rubarbe, Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, Sene, Scammonie</hi> (whereof your <hi>Diagredium</hi> is prepared) to be vſed in <hi>Febribus colica Nephri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide,</hi> then an whole ounce either of <hi>Catholicon Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedicta</hi> or <hi>Diaphaenian,</hi> &amp; not onely more profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the partie, but more pleaſant, in that they are ſmall in quantitie, pleaſant in taſt, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:4664:11"/>
any lothſome ſmell. And beſides al this more eaſe and profite will enſue to the Apothecarie, in that he ſhall not euery yeare be driuen to ſearch his boxes, and throw away ſo much as he findes euill (which muſt be done in your purgations.) But our extractions wilbe as perfect 20. yeares after, as they were at the beginning when they were firſt drawen. In ſo much as we doo not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly finde fault with that which is ill, but we bring alſo that which is better in place, why ſhould you be angrie or grieued with vs at all? If you were but reaſonable men, you would in ſome meaſure requite our pains, at the leaſt with good words. Thus much co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning your purgations.</p>
            <p>Concerning your <hi>Comfortatiues,</hi> as <hi>elect de gem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis, Dia ambrae, dia Margarit: de cocco Daphn:</hi> and ſuch like, wherwith you are commonly accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſtrengthen ſuch parts as you ſee weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, I am very loth to ſay my mind, for that I am aſſured that I haue not a litle mooued you with that which before I haue ſpoken; notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, in that the commoditie &amp; vſe thereof ſhall redound to the good of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth, and publike ſafety of all, which things both you &amp; I ought to ſeeke being both of vs ſubiects &amp; me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof: I hope it ſhall neither be from my purpoſe, no new fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gled toy, nor to be reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, though I do lay open before your eies thoſe errors which haue bene &amp; are daily committed in preparation of theſe alſo. And that I may in
<pb facs="tcp:4664:11"/>
breefe manner make demonſtration therof, you know that theſe are commonly compounded of hearbes, rootes, ſpices, ſtones, and ſometimes of mettals, which by ancient experience haue bene found to haue ſome vertue in them, to comfort this or that principal part. As for the hearbes &amp; rootes, you may gather by thoſe pointes which haue beene before ſet downe concerning your ſirrupes, that firſt of al before they be miniſtred, there muſt be ſeperation made of the vertue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the venome, the vicious &amp; bad from the pure ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent &amp; good: which being done you ſhall find <hi>Meliſſa in Doronico,</hi> &amp; contrariwiſe <hi>Doronicum in Meliſſa,</hi> although <hi>Meliſſa</hi> is not ſo manifeſtly to be ſeene in <hi>Doronico,</hi> nor <hi>Doronicum in Meliſſa.</hi> If <hi>Mathiolus</hi> had ſeene this ſecreet coniunction of nature, hee would neuer haue called <hi>Doronicum, Daemoniaecum.</hi> Likewiſe <hi>Been album &amp; rubrum</hi> haue their impurities, which in any caſe muſt be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away before they bee brought to compoſition. Moreouer if fiue pound of Cinnamon haue but one ounce of vertue, two pound of Nutmegs as much, three pound of Cloues no more, what ſhould all the reſt do in the receipt, which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worth, but tendeth onely to putrifaction. Conſider wel with your ſelf, muſt not that needs be a ſingular balme, one ounce whereof will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue &amp; whole pound of droſſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> putrifaction a dozen yeare, it is not ſo in Cinnamon, for take a dram out of the pound, and the reſt will indure
<pb facs="tcp:4664:12"/>
iuſt two dayes: the like is to be ſayd of all your ſpices whatſoeuer. Now for the ſtones and met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talline leaues, as leafe gold, leafe ſiluer, &amp;c: there is an other thing worthie of reproofe therein (wherof we haue not yet ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) which is <hi>Coagula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> We denie not but conſent with you in this, that there is great vertue in gold to comfort the hart, ſo is there in pearels, corrall, in the Saphire againſt poiſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, likewiſe in the <hi>Hiacinth</hi> &amp; <hi>Smaragd</hi> againſt the <hi>Epilepſie</hi> and <hi>Melancolie,</hi> in the <hi>Iaſpis</hi> to help digeſtion, in <hi>Chriſtall</hi> againſt the ſtone, in <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pide linceo Iudaico,</hi> of <hi>Lapide Spongiae</hi> the like vertue is found. But except you can prooue that the ſtomacke of man is able to digeſt them, that is, diſſolue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (which is alwaies performed in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion) which I am ſure you can neuer doo: we will neuer grant vnto you that the body can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue any helpe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeeme they neuer ſo good &amp; wholeſome. For daily experience teacheth vs, that though a man eate good and nouriſhing meate, yet if the ſame digeſt not in his ſtomack, it doth not onely hinder the vertue nutritiue in the body, but putteth that partie ſo affected, in danger of his life: ſo that when you are called to ſuch a patient, you make that a very dangerous matter, &amp; not without cauſe: Euen ſo do we af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that theſe ſtones which are taken into the body &amp; vndigeſted, do not onely denie comfort &amp; helpe thereunto, but (though they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tity) if they were not expelled by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:4664:12"/>
would greatly hurt the partie: yea it hath beene ſeene that the leaues of gold haue ſo ſticke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſſdes of the ſtomack, that digeſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath bin hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered therby a lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g time after-And as litle is ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gold, pearles, corrall, chriſtall, the rubie, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phire, ſmaragd, &amp;c. digeſted &amp; diminiſhed in the ſtomacke, as it is diſſolued in boyling either in coollis or broth: which thing you haue ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted but vnto ſmal or no profit. Thus may you ſee deare Coſin y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> watchfulnes &amp; charines of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for that the cofers wherin ſhe hath put theſe cures of moſt da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous diſeaſes, as <hi>Epilepſia, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancho: Ietharg, Paralicis, Lepra, Mania,</hi> and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, are by her as by a faithfull keeper, ſo faſt locked &amp; bound by coagulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that it is vnpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for the ſtomack of an healthy man to picke them open, much leſſe of him that is ſicke. Yet if you will well behold, you ſhall ſee that with this her neernes and warines, there is ioined libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie: for though ſhe hath locked theſe cofers, yet hath ſhe left the keyes with vs: but you are ſo ſlouthful that rather then you wil take any pains to ſeeke them, you wil cauſe your patients to eat cofers and all and bid nature vnlocke them if ſhe will, when (alas poore wench) ſhee hath not the keies her ſelfe, but is inforced to throw them out again to ſmal or no profit, &amp; to her great diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we then ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence the infinit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of theſe <hi>Vulcaniſts</hi> &amp; painful ſmiths, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d day take paines to blow the coles, to
<pb facs="tcp:4664:13"/>
file vs fit keies for euery locke, one for Chriſtall, another for Corrall, one for Pearles, another for the Adamant, one for Siluer, another for Gold, &amp; ſo for ſundry lockes ſundry keies. And as a cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſmith makes diuers locks one like another, &amp; to euery locke a ſeuerall key, yet he will make one key ſo curiouſly that it wil open them all: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo nature imitated of many, but ſurpaſſed of none, though ſhe hath for diuerſe lockes made ſundry keies, yet hath ſhe one key that will vndoe them all. Theſe keies ought euery expert &amp; true Phiſicia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue alwaies ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging at his girdle, that as oft as neede requireth hee might goe to the cheſts of nature, &amp; fetch <hi>Magiſters, Eſſences, Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, Elixirs,</hi> &amp; ſuch like: Then would you ſoone ſhew your <hi>Diamargariton,</hi> your <hi>Aromatica,</hi> your <hi>Exhilerantia,</hi> in that you ſhould find more vertue in an ounce of the eſſence of Pearle or Corrall, then in the whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſition either of <hi>Coccy Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliuy,</hi> or <hi>Mithridati</hi> &amp; more ſtrength in one ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the ſolution of the <hi>Smaragd, Hiacinth, Sardi</hi> or <hi>Granate,</hi> then in an whole pound of your <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>margar:</hi> or <hi>Elect. de gem:</hi> and more vertue in two drams in the ſolution of <hi>Lapis Linceius iudaici ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia Chriſtallorum,</hi> then in the whole receit of your <hi>Elect, iuſtini,</hi> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Thus may you ſee the force of your medecines according to their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: you may perceaue by that which hath beene, ſpoken that your ſirrupes be but ſauces, your purgations for the moſt part poiſons, and
<pb facs="tcp:4664:13"/>
that your <hi>Confertatiues, Exhileratiues,</hi> &amp; <hi>Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues,</hi> are by nature ſo faſt fettred that they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not once moue againſt their enemies. I haue tolde you that the remedies for the two formoſt is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, and for the other ſolution.</p>
            <p>Yet you haue one ſorte of medecines which you are wont to miniſter when al the reſt will do no good, wherof a word or two &amp; ſo an end. Theſe are called <hi>Anodina</hi> and <hi>Narcotica,</hi> of which ſort are <hi>Philonium, Requies, Eſdra,</hi> &amp; others; the chiefe actors therein are <hi>Opium, Mandrake</hi> &amp; <hi>Poppie,</hi> which are moſt manifeſt poyſons, which is argued not onely by the terrible &amp; dangerous operations which they effect, but to your curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous corrections with <hi>Caſtorie, Mirrhe, Saffron,</hi> &amp;c: and by your wordes, for you aduiſe men not to vſe them but in great neceſſitie, yea neuer to vſe them without wiſe forecaſt &amp; deepe conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. But if men would be ruled by that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile which is more ſafe, they ſhould neuer med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with them at all, vnleſſe they knew a better way to correct them then that before ſpecified. For as I haue ſaid before, theſe correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions are no true mitigations of the venome, but by palliations to deceaue the outward ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but euery true correction is done by ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and ſubſtraction. The like is to be done in <hi>Opium, Mandrake</hi> and <hi>Popie:</hi> for if you let the ſtinking <hi>Mercurie</hi> of <hi>Opium</hi> flee away, and lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide his <hi>Diaphoreticall ſalt</hi> for another purpoſe,
<pb facs="tcp:4664:14"/>
you ſhall then haue a pure <hi>Narcoticall Sulphure,</hi> which by himſelfe may be ſafely giuen inwardly to aſſwage any paine whatſoeuer, In like ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner may you vſe <hi>Mandrake</hi> and <hi>Popie,</hi> whereunto as vnto the reſt, you may adde the tinctures of <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, Cinnamon, Cloues,</hi> and ſuch like: ſo ſhall you haue <hi>Anodina comforta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia</hi> &amp; <hi>Exhilarantia</hi> in one medecine. So ſhall you not neede to ſtay a long ſeaſon for the mellowing of them, but may mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter them preſently if need require.</p>
            <p>Theſe few lines I truſt will perſwade you, and cauſe you to confeſſe that you haue a long time erred in the preparation of al your medecines. But I feare you are ſo deepely grounded in the principles, the foggie miſts and bogges of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle, Galene,</hi> &amp;c. that you are fully reſolued that theſe ſimples which we cal venemous, are ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of the foure Elements into one ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, that there ought not to be any ſeparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made, but they muſt be corrected by additions. O what impietie is this, that ſuch as are called to the knowledge &amp; profeſſion of God and his word, ſhould giue more credite vnto theſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Infidels, then to his ſacred &amp; bleſſed word? why ſhould wee be Infidels in our philoſophie and Chriſtians by name, only in reſpect of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters concerning eternitie? why ſhould we be as Chriſtians in matters of the ſoule, &amp; as Infidels in things belonging to the body? why ſhould we be as profeſſors of holy religion in our meeting
<pb facs="tcp:4664:14"/>
together after the manner of Chriſtians on the Lords day, and all the daies of the weeke after be as Infidels in the things concerning the bodie, which God hath framed as the houſe of the ſoule? Dooth not <hi>Moſes</hi> that heauenly philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher record that God beheld al things which he made, and loe they were exceeding good. How dare you then affirme, that <hi>Opium, Mercury, Arſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick,</hi> or any thing els is except. If they were good then doth that goodneſſe ſtill remaine in them: how then commeth it to paſſe that they are ſuch ſtrong poyſons? if you ſeeke the cauſe thereof in <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> or <hi>Galene,</hi> you ſhall neuer finde it: for herein they were as blind as beetels, being alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether depriued of ſuch knowledge, vnto whom God vouchſafed not to impart the ſame, &amp; yet left them inexcuſable againſt the day of their appearing before the dreadfull Maieſtie of that great God, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt. But let vs take our way vnto the worde of God (which will fully reſolue all men that beleeue it) which telleth vs that for the tranſgreſſion of one, not onely death was enioined vnto him, but for his fault, euery creature hath a deth inflicted vpon him, each creature had an euill ioyned to his good, but like vnto like, vnto ſtrong life was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſtrong death or venome, for the death of Roſes is not ſo ſtrong as the death of Arſenicke; which may bee perceaued hereby, in that the balme of Arſenick is far ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger then the balme
<pb facs="tcp:4664:15"/>
of roſes, as the life or balme of roſes is inferiour to the balme of Arſenick, which is of ſuch force that he is able to preſerue from death &amp; diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion many yeares, that moſt ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g poiſon which is ioyned with him, whereby wee may perceiue that in the ſtrongeſt poyſons are the moſt pure &amp; ſweeteſt balmes to be found. But of this you ſhal heare more in my <hi>Anatomy of death.</hi> Now we may ſee that before the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> all thinges were good, all things came vnto him and were bred vnto his hand without his labour. But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward part of it was ioyned to poiſon, part of it ſo faſt lockt vp, that without great ſweate of browes he ſhould not eat of it. And in theſe our latter dayes ſloth is growen ſo ſtrong<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; idlenes hath gotten ſuch maiſterie, that there are very few which will let one drop fal fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their browes to ſeeke this bread, but indeuour by all metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicall meanes to maintaine this idlenes, and to continue it after their accuſtomed manner, that they may ſit in their chambers on a ſoft cuſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; take pen &amp; inke &amp; a litle paper, ſetting downe their preſcriptions to their Poticaries. <hi>℞ <hi>rad. flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res Semina, &amp;c.</hi>
               </hi> Theſe men do not onely neglect their dutie themſelues, but with might &amp; maine they ſeeke to deface thoſe (which ſpare for no coſtes or labour to earne their bread in this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner) by raiſing of ill reports againſt them, whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering in the eares of the Honorable, &amp; telling them that we are mad men, that we do &amp; ſay we
<pb facs="tcp:4664:15"/>
know not what, &amp; are not worthie to liue in a common-wealth, Howſoeuer other men be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, I pray you be not angry, I haue a better opinion of you, I doubt not but you thinke as wel of <hi>Paracelſus</hi> as his great frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d <hi>Eraſmus</hi> doth, which could not chooſe but commend his dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in preparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his medecines, &amp; iudged them farre to exceede thoſe which were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly vſed. At this time I craue no more at your hands, but patiently to heare me, and read that which I haue here ſet you downe: neither will I at this preſent trouble your head with any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther declaration of the matters before ſpoken of, nor in prouing vnto you how farre you haue erred in bringing in your humors intemperie &amp; obſtructions to be the cauſes of all diſeaſes, that they be but fantaſticall inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tions of an idle head, hauing no foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in nature, I know I ſhould but anger you, or tell you pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radoxes to proue, that neither <hi>Apoplexia, Epilep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, Melancolia, Mania, Paralycis, Lithargas, Pleuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, Peripneumonia, Peſtis, Sincope, Colica, Iliaca, Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteria, Diarhaea, Gonorrhaea, Nephritis, Stranguria, Diſſuria, Cachexia, Hydrops, Icterus ater &amp; flaum, Febris, Diaria, Quotidiana, Tertiana, Quartana, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctica, Lepra, Vlcera, Apoſtemata,</hi> or any other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe whatſoeuer, are the proper death or ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of <hi>Microcoſmi,</hi> but are the ſickneſſes and death of the fruit of <hi>Microcoſmi,</hi> &amp; that by tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantation they growe in <hi>Microcoſmus.</hi> Hardly
<pb facs="tcp:4664:16"/>
would you beleeue that <hi>Eſtis</hi> is the deth of Arſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick. <hi>Pluritis</hi> the death of Antimonie. <hi>Prunella</hi> the death of Brimſtone. <hi>Epilepſia</hi> the death of <hi>Vitriole. Colica, Podagra, Gonagra, Chiragra, Iſchias. Arthritis, Hemicrania,</hi> the death of <hi>Tartar. Morbus gallicus,</hi> the death of <hi>Mercury. Lethar,</hi> the death of <hi>Opiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Febris,</hi> the death of <hi>Nitroci ſulphuris. Vlcera,</hi> the death of <hi>Saltes,</hi> &amp;c. And if you had beſtowed but half your ſtudie in the firſt booke of Moſes, which you ſpent in the fooliſh Philoſophie of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> you had eſpied your errors long agoe. I haue told you already, &amp; yet I grieue not to tel you againe, that for the offence of our firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, death was not onely laid vpon them, but for the ſame tranſgreſſion God planted a death in euery thing he had made, in euery thing he put a death able to deſtroy ſuch a life. And theſe deaths were not, nether are they dead deaths, but quicke &amp; liue deaths, &amp; they tooke power both of multiplication and tranſplantation of him which ſent them. This is the cauſe that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dieth ſuch ſundry deaths, becauſe hee eateth in his bread the death of all other things, which when perfect ſeparation is not made, bringeth foorth fruit according to his kinde. Ouer theſe deaths hath the Phyſician power, and not ouer that which was inioyned to the body of man parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly. Therfore we affirme that neither <hi>Poda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gra, Hidrops, Lepra</hi> or <hi>Epilepſia,</hi> are vncurable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, the reaſon is, for that (as I ſayd before)
<pb facs="tcp:4664:16"/>
they are the death of the fruites of the great world, &amp; not of man, &amp; that they grow not na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally in man but come in by tranſplantation, &amp; therefore may be ſeperated. But ſoft a litle, I thinke I haue angred you before I was aware, wherefore I will imitate the wiſe &amp; skilfull Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion, who when hee ſeeth a great deale of proude fleſh in an vlcer, will not apply a ſtrong coroſiue to take it away at once, although need ſhould ſo require, but will by litle &amp; litle apply his corroſiue, as well to keepe the good will &amp; fauour of his patient, as to prefer his owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite. Euen ſo I ſeing theſe cancred opinions graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp; rooted in you, thinke it beſt rather to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh it by litle &amp; litle, then violently at once to pull it away, leaſt thereby I ſhould purchaſe your diſpleaſure, which I am very loth to doo. But if I ſhall perceaue that you will giue theſe my ſimple letters the ſecond or third reading ouer, you ſhall not onely encourage mee in my next labours, to ſet out particularly and plainly that which I haue now haſtily truſt vp hard in a bundell (cutting it as ſhorte as poſſibly I could, doubting how you would take it) but it will prouoke me to reueale vnto you the true and perfect preparation of ſuch rare medecines which are found out by this arte of ſeparation, ſo called becauſe it doth ſhewe the way how to ſeperate the good from the bad, &amp; not to make that which is e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, as ſome haue falſly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood.
<pb facs="tcp:4664:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
And the more perfect that the ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, the more worthy name it receiueth: as for example, if Antimonie be ſo purged, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any euident annoyance it may be inwardly taken, then is he ſaid to be in his magiſter, but if he be further purged one degree higher, then is he in his eſſence. Nowe if you leaue him not there, but do purifie him more, then doth his tincture appeare: and if you can purge him throughly and perfectly then ſhall you haue his <hi>Arcanum,</hi> &amp; ſo of others. There are alſo theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees in ſolucion, whereby the eſſence of gold ſurpaſſeth the Magiſter, &amp; both are expelled by his tincture.</p>
            <p>Thus leauing of at this time to trouble you, I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit you vnto the tuition &amp; protection of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, who for his ſonne Chriſt his ſake inſpire you with his holy ſpirit, whereby mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all loue may bee increaſed in thoſe that are his, that in things concerning their owne &amp; other mens ſoules &amp; bodies, they may agree &amp; be of one minde, that God may haue the glory by their actions in this life, and afterward they may through Chriſts merits attaine euerlaſting hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe. From my houſe at S. the 21. of this preſent March. 1586.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your louing Cooſin and freend, ſtudent in Phyſicke. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4664:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
